<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copy of a letter from an eminent commander in Sir Thomas Fairfax army, to severall worthy members of the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament. Dated at Marston, within a mile and a little more of Oxford, May 24. 1645. Wherein is fully related the return of Lieutenant Gen. Crumwell, and Major Gen. Brown, and their joyning with Sir Thomas Fairfax at Marston aforesaid. The Lord Gorings returne into Gloucestershire, the Kings forces advance into Darbyshire, Secretary Nicholas his letters intercepted, the taking of Philpot the Kings Harrold at Armes, and sundry other doctors. The taking of Wolvercote house, which the enemy set on fire, but was quenched by our forces, and therein the Deputy-governour, divers other prisoners, and all their armes and ammunition. Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Eminent commander in Sir Thomas Fairfax army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E285_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200072</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860876</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860876</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113003</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80457)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113003)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E285[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copy of a letter from an eminent commander in Sir Thomas Fairfax army, to severall worthy members of the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament. Dated at Marston, within a mile and a little more of Oxford, May 24. 1645. Wherein is fully related the return of Lieutenant Gen. Crumwell, and Major Gen. Brown, and their joyning with Sir Thomas Fairfax at Marston aforesaid. The Lord Gorings returne into Gloucestershire, the Kings forces advance into Darbyshire, Secretary Nicholas his letters intercepted, the taking of Philpot the Kings Harrold at Armes, and sundry other doctors. The taking of Wolvercote house, which the enemy set on fire, but was quenched by our forces, and therein the Deputy-governour, divers other prisoners, and all their armes and ammunition. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Eminent commander in Sir Thomas Fairfax army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Cotes in the Old-baily.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 27".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113003:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Copy of A LETTER FROM An eminent Commander in Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> Army, to ſeverall worthy Members of the Honourable Houſe of Commons aſſembled in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Dated at Marſton, within a mile and little more of Oxford, May 24. 1645.</p>
            <p>Wherein is fully related the return of Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Gen. <hi>Crumwell,</hi> and Major Gen. <hi>Brown,</hi> and their joyning with Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> at Marſton aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Gorings</hi> returne into Glouceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, the Kings forces advance into Darbyſhire, Secretary <hi>Nicholas</hi> his Letters intercepted, the taking of <hi>Philpet</hi> the Kings Harrold at Armes, and fundry other Doctors. The taking of Wolvercote houſe, which the enemy ſet on fire, but was quenched by our forces, and therein the Deputy-governour, divers other priſoners, and all their Armes and Ammunition.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <add>May 27</add> 
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Coles</hi> in the Old-baily. 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113003:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113003:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Tudor rose surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Scottish thistle surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>French fleur-de-lis surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Irish harp surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He laſt night Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> our Generall came to Marſton, within a mile and little more of Oxford, the 22 of <hi>May</hi> inſtant, where Lieutenant Generall <hi>Crumwell</hi> and Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Browne</hi> met him, the Foot were quartered in ſeverall Towns about a mile and halfe from Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, our Horſe-guards and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113003:3"/>within twice Musket-ſhot of the Workes. The enemy hath drowned the meddowes as much as they can, and fired the Suburbs, and have burnt a Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mill the laſt night, and this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſet on fire a Garriſon at VVolvercoate which they had within a mile, which is burning at the writing hereof. They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have burnt the Towne, and other Townes hereabouts, but our Forces being poſſeſſed thereof, have prevented their evill intentions. Yeſterday, as our Generall was on the Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-greene viewing the workes at Magdalen-Colledge, a Bullet weighing eight pound was ſhot at him, but went over his head
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113003:3"/>and did no hurt to any of the reſt, though hee ſtood within twice Musket-ſhot of the VVorkes; this day hee was within twice Piſtoll-ſhot of the VVorkes at the other end of the Towne, but they were ſparing of Powder. The Souldiers are intrenching their head Quarters and making a bridge over the water, to hold a correſpondency with the other Forces on the other ſide of the River. <hi>Goring</hi> is come into Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſterſhire wee expect his Horſe ſuddenly: yet if yee ſend Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaries from London and other Counties, wee make no doubt to make ſhort worke of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, either by gaining of the Towne, or by being Maſters of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113003:4"/>the field, if the enemy advance to fight with us.</p>
            <p>This day, <hi>May</hi> the 24. we have intelligence that the Kings For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are advanced into Derbiſhire, and ſo Northward, as wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, if the beſieging of Oxford divert not their intentions; letters from Secretary <hi>Nicholas</hi> were this day intercepted, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palleſt matter they contained was intelligence of paſſages in both Houſes. The Lord <hi>Cotting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> and all the Lords and Gallants beare Armes in Oxford. VVee have taken <hi>Philpot</hi> the Harrold, and ſome ſtragling Doctors that were fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of a ſiege. As ſoone as the bridges be made, (the want of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113003:4"/>boats much retarding the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice) there will bee communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation from one Quarter to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and then fit for making approaches neerer. VVe quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the fire yeſterday, and took the Deputy-Governour and all the Armes and Ammunition in the houſe at VVolvercoate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fire got to it.</p>
            <p>The Generall going to Burſtall houſe to view the workes, and to ſettle a guard to keepe the garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Souldiers within, that the paſſage might be open betweene Alisbury and the Army, and ſo to London, Captaine <hi>Flemming</hi> Adjutant generall of Horſe was ſhot in the belly, we thinke mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, he adventured further then
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113003:5"/>his Commiſsion, and the unruli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Horſe brought him among the enemy unawares, he was a very active and ſtout Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Marſton, <date>May 24. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
